It has been roughly one century since the Apollo moon landing.
アポロ:Apollo program/Project Apollo, 着陸[ちゃくりく]:landing/alighting/touch down, 果たす[はたす]:to accomplish/to achieve|to do ... completely, 世紀[せいき]:century/era
（ナレーション）アポロが
月着陸を果たしてから ほぼ１世紀
People, energy, garbage, and many other things have all begun to spread out into space.
エネルギー:energy
人も エネルギーも ゴミも―
あらゆる:all/every, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 広がる[ひろがる]:to spread (out)/to extend/to stretch
あらゆるものが
宇宙へと広がりつつありました
And behind the scenes, the economic and technological gap...
陰[いん]:yin (i.e. the negative)|unseen location (i.e. somewhere private), 陰[かげ]:shade/shadow|other side
そして その陰で―
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 各国[かっこく, かくこく]:each nation|many nations/many countries, 経済[けいざい]:economics/business/finance, 科学[かがく]:science, 格差[かくさ]:qualitative difference/disparity
世界各国の
経済 科学などの格差もまた―
...between the countries of the world has also spread wider.
広がる[ひろがる]:to spread (out)/to extend/to stretch
広がったのです
It is at a time such as this that the Von Braun, mankind's first manned explorer to Jupiter,
そんな中―
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 初[はつ, うい]:first/new, 初[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 往還[おうかん]:traffic/coming and going/highway, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
人類初の木星往還船
フォン･ブラウン号が―
...is about to set sail,
旅立つ[たびだつ]:to begin a trip/to depart|to die, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
旅立とうとしています
...carrying with it humanity's hopes and dreams.
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 野心[やしん]:ambition/aspiration|sinister designs, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
人類の夢と野心を乗せて
Gotta go faster...
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
（ハチマキ）もっと早く
Gotta push myself harder...
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 力強い[ちからづよい]:powerful/strong|reassuring
もっと力強く
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 遠く[とおく]:far away/distant/at a distance
もっと遠くへ
Gotta go further!
That's the kinda ship the Von Braun is...
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
フォン･ブラウンっていうのは
そういう船なんだ
Did you see that vector change just now?
試験官[しけんかん]:examiner, 方向転換[ほうこうてんかん]:change of course
（試験官１）
見ましたか？ 今の方向転換
試験官[しけんかん]:examiner, 推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant
（試験官２）
ああ 推進剤を使わなかったな
Yeah. He didn't use any propellant at all.
星野(ほしの)八郎太(はちろうた)
Hoshino Hachirota... He hasn't made any mistakes in the EVA exam so far.
審査[しんさ]:judging/inspection/examination
ＥＶＡ審査では
ここまで ノーミスですね
He worked in Technora's Debris Section for four years. Resigned last month, huh?
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), 勤務[きんむ]:service/duty/work, 先月[せんげつ]:last month, 退職[たいしょく]:retirement/resignation
テクノーラのデブリ課に
４年間勤務 先月 退職か
His remaining propellant, oxygen, and time aren't too shabby at all.
推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant, 残量[ざんりょう]:remaining quantity/residual quantity, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), タイム:time, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
推進剤残量 酸素残量 タイム
どれも悪くない
試験官[しけんかん]:examiner, 学科[がっか]:study subject/course of study|department (university, etc.)
（試験官２）学科が ちとアレだが
いいとこまで行くんじゃないか？
His academics are a little weak, but I think this guy has the right stuff, don't you?
試験官[しけんかん]:examiner
（試験官１）ええ
Yeah.
（ハチマキ）んんっ…
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
Phase 20
Tentative Steps
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!, あああ:Aah!/Ooh!/Oh No!
（新入社員）
うわああああ…
Somebody stop me!
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, 社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
誰か止めてくれ！
（社員１）うわっ
Grab onto the bars!
Use the bars!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
（社員２）バーにつかまれ バーに
Geez, my hair is a mess!
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire, 髪[かみ]:hair (on the head)
（新入社員１）
もう 髪 グッチャグチャ
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire, スプレー:spray
（新入社員２）だから
スプレーしとけって言ったのに
That's why I told you to use spray on it before we left!
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire, 等身大[とうしんだい]:life-size/life-sized
（新入社員３）
見て ノーラ君だよ 等身大
Look, it's a Nora-kun!
A life-sized one!
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
（新入社員４）近くで見るの初めて
I've never seen one up close before.
Where's Public Relations Section?
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire, 広報[こうほう]:public relations/PR/publicity, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（新入社員１）広報課ってどこ？
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire, 受付[うけつけ]:reception (desk)/information desk|receipt, 真下[ました]:right under/directly below
（新入社員２）
ほら ここ 受付の真下
Look, it's right here.
Right below reception.
Wow, this place is pretty big.
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire, 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 広い[ひろい]:spacious/vast/wide
（新入社員３）結構 広いんだ
研修[けんしゅう]:training (esp. in-service)/induction course, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, 配属[はいぞく]:assignment (of a person to somewhere)/attachment (of a person to another unit, organization, etc.), 時期[じき]:time/season|soon
（リュシー）そうか
研修 終わって 配属の時期か
Oh, right. Training's ended, and people are getting their new assignments.
I wonder if we were ever like that...
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
（シャポウ）
私たちも あんな感じだったのかな
Yeah, it's been a year.
１年たったんだね
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 実感[じっかん]:real feeling/actual feeling|to actually feel
（タナベ）もう１年たつなんて
あんまり実感がないな
It hardly seems like it's been a year already.
I wonder if I've matured a bit as a person...
成長[せいちょう]:growth/grow to adulthood
（タナベ）
ちょっとは成長したのかな
Hi! Welcome! Welcome!
（ラビィ）はい～
ようこそ:welcome!/nice to see you!
♪ようこそ ようこそ
あっ
すてき:lovely/dreamy/beautiful, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 愉快[ゆかい]:pleasant/happy
（ラビィ）♪すてきなデブリ課
愉快なデブリ課
The wonderful Debris Section, the happy Debris Section,
...gives you a hearty, thankful welcome!
熱烈[ねつれつ]:ardent/passionate/vehement, 御礼[おれい, おんれい]:thanks|manners|bow||
♪熱烈御礼
- Thankful welcome!
大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 歓迎[かんげい]:welcome/reception
（ラビィ･課長）♪大歓迎
痛[いた]:ouch/ow/that hurt, 痛[つう]:pain/ache/-algia
（課長）あ痛っ…
（ラビィ）あれ？
Oops.
What in the world's all this about?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
（タナベ）何なんですか？ 一体
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), 歓迎[かんげい]:welcome/reception
（ユーリ）新人の歓迎だよ
（タナベ）え？
Our welcoming ceremony for new employees.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
（課長）
ごめんね 愛(あい)ちゃんのときは―
We're sorry. When you were assigned here, Ai-chan, we didn't expect you to actually show up.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
まさか本当に来るとは
思ってなかったからさあ
連続[れんぞく]:serial/consecutive/continuity, 新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), 夢[ゆめ]:dream, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
いやあ ２年連続の新人
夢みたいですなあ
Wow, new workers two years in a row!
I must be dreaming!
New worker? You don't mean as a replacement for Senpai, do you?!
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ...
（タナベ）
新人って まさか先輩の代わり？
Well, um... There are only so many sick days and personal days that he can take.
有休[ゆうきゅう]:paid vacation/paid holiday, 代休[だいきゅう]:compensatory holiday (for working on a day off), 限界[げんかい]:limit/bound
（課長）あっ え その…
有休と代休にも限界が
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 純粋[じゅんすい]:pure/true/genuine, 増員[ぞういん]:increase the number of personnel
（ユーリ）
でも今回は 純粋な増員ですよね
But this new worker is simply here to increase our staff, right?
そうそう:so long/so often|oh, yes!, そうそう:funeral/burial rites|attendance at a funeral
（ラビィ）そうそう
That's right. They value our services as the people who found that INTO mine.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 我々[われわれ]:we, 活躍[かつやく]:activity (esp. energetic)/great efforts|to flourish, 評価[ひょうか]:valuation|to value|to appreciate
連合の機雷を見つけた我々の活躍が
評価されたのさ
（フィー）よく言うよ
Yeah, I'll just bet...
Tanabe, have you heard from Hachimaki?
The first round of testing is over, right?
ハチマキ:headband, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
タナベ
ハチマキから連絡ないのか？
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
１次試験 終わったんだろ？
He probably failed and is too embarrassed to call us.
落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ラビィ）落ちたんで
バツが悪いんじゃないの？
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped
（課長）
どんな形でも 戻ってきてくれると
助かるんだけどねえ
I'd be glad to have him back in any capacity.
You don't think he'd commit suicide out of disgrace, do you?
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure, 自殺[じさつ]:suicide
まさか カッコつかなくて自殺？
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
ちょっと課長
Careful, Chief...
（タナベ）大丈夫ですよ
He'll be fine.
（ラビィ）あっ？
Senpai isn't that weak a person.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate
先輩は
そんなに弱くはありません あっ…
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate
先輩は
そんなに弱くはありません あっ…
It's the new guy for sure this time!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
今度こそ 来ましたよ
（課長）うん
Tanabe-kun, get out of the doorway!
（ラビィ）タナベ君 どいて
（タナベ）あっ はい
Oh. Right!
Hi! Welcome! Welcome!
はい～
ようこそ:welcome!/nice to see you!
♪ようこそ ようこそ
The wonderful Debris Section, the happy Debris Section,
すてき:lovely/dreamy/beautiful, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 愉快[ゆかい]:pleasant/happy
♪すてきなデブリ課
愉快なデブリ課
...gives you a hearty, thankful welcome!
熱烈[ねつれつ]:ardent/passionate/vehement, 御礼[おれい, おんれい]:thanks|manners|bow||
♪熱烈御礼
- Thankful welcome!
大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 歓迎[かんげい]:welcome/reception
（課長･ラビィ）♪大歓迎
う？
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
あれ？
（ラビィ）管制課の
Huh?
You're that girl from...
歓迎会[かんげいかい]:welcome party, 新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards)
（ユーリ）
あっ 歓迎会なんですよ 新人の
Oh... We're sorry, it's our welcoming ceremony for new employees.
決して[けっして, けして]:never/by no means/not in the least, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
うん そうそう
決して遊んでるわけじゃ
That's right! We weren't playing around or anything.
担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（フィー）何だい
また うちの担当に戻ったの？
What's up? You here to watch over our shoulders again?
I'm Claire Rondo. I've been assigned to work here at Debris Section.
度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 配属[はいぞく]:assignment (of a person to somewhere)/attachment (of a person to another unit, organization, etc.)
（クレア）この度
デブリ課に配属となりました―
ロンド:rondo
クレア･ロンドです
（課長･ラビィ）えっ！？
Wait, so the new employee is...
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards)
じゃあ 新人って…
I look forward to working with all of you.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
よろしく お願いします
（一同）ええーっ！？
This is an announcement from the examination committee.
Examiners who haven't attended post-redesign reevaluation task guidance sessions,
（ハキム）これもいいかな
Mind if I throw this one in, too?
（男性）はい どうも
Sure. Thanks.
Sorry for the trouble.
...make sure to submit an attendance request form before the end of third term testing.
いいえ:no/nay|well
（ハキム）すまんね
（係員）いいえ
That's okay.
Hakim!
（ハチマキ）ハキム
Looks like the isolated environment test is about to start.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 閉鎖[へいさ]:closing/closure/shutdown, 環境[かんきょう]:environment/circumstance, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
そろそろ
閉鎖環境試験 始まるらしいぞ
Attention, all members of the press.
You must have a lot of spare time, Hoshino.
余裕[よゆう]:surplus/margin|composure, わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
（ハキム）余裕だな 星野
わざわざ呼びに来てくれたのか？
Today's public testing is now ended. We ask that you please leave the examination block.
You came here to tell me that?
As if.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 蹴落とす[けおとす]:to kick down/to defeat
（ハチマキ）まさか 俺は１次で
友達を蹴落としてるんだ
Back during the first round,
I beat out a friend of mine.
I don't care about anybody but myself.
関心[かんしん]:concern/interest
自分のことしか関心ねえよ
This is an official announcement.
That's good to hear.
（ハキム）それでいい
（ハチマキ）あっ？
Test module reconfiguration work is scheduled to begin tomorrow morning...
Neither do I.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
（ハキム）私も同じだ
For the next ten days, we will have you live in those modules in teams of four.
日間[ひあい]:number of days/period of days|daily interest rate, 日間[にっかん]:daytime/during the day, 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 組になる[くみになる]:to join forces with/to cooperate with
（ドルフ）これより10日間
皆さんには ４人１組になって―
モジュール:module, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
あのモジュールで
生活してもらいます
In this test, you will not be evaluated as individuals, but rather as a team.
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 評価[ひょうか]:valuation|to value|to appreciate, 対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), 個人[こじん]:individual/private person/personal, チーム:team
（ドルフ）今回の評価対象は
個人ではなくチームです
If a single member of the team leaves the module before the ten days are up,
期間[きかん]:period/term/interval, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, モジュール:module, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|, 場合[ばあい]:case/situation
期間内に １人でも
モジュールから離れた場合は―
...the entire team will be disqualified.
チーム:team, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, まとめる:to collect/to put (it all) together|to summarize, 失格[しっかく]:disqualification/elimination/incapacity (legal)
チーム全員 まとめて失格とします
見知る[みしる]:to recognise/to recognize/to know by sight, チームワーク:teamwork, 取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||
見知らぬ人間と
チームワークを取れってか
He wants us to work as a team with total strangers, huh?
以内[いない]:within/inside of/less than
（ドルフ）
では これから 15分以内に―
All right, please enter your modules through the airlock that matches your test number.
それぞれ:each/respectively, 受験番号[じゅけんばんごう]:examinee's (seat) number, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, ナンバー:number, エアロック:air lock
それぞれの受験番号と
同じナンバーのエアロックから―
モジュール:module, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
モジュールに入ってください
Very well, begin the test.
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 開始[かいし]:start/commencement/beginning
それでは 試験開始
102...
102…
（ハチマキ）何だよ
Well, I'll be. The test modules are exposed to space, huh?
テスト:test, モジュール:module, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, むき出し[むきだし]:naked/bare|frank
テストモジュールは
宇宙にむき出しか
ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 緊張感[きんちょうかん]:feeling of tension/air of tension/tension
まっ これぐらいのほうが
緊張感あっていいけど
Well, I guess it's better this way.
It'll keep us on our toes.
（サリー）ん？
You sure got here fast.
I thought I'd be the first on board.
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 一番乗り[いちばんのり]:leader of a charge/first to arrive
（ハチマキ）早いな
俺が一番乗りかと思ったら
Sally Silverstone. I worked as a contractor to CalTech as a mission specialist.
サリー:sari, シルバー:silver, ストーン:stone
（サリー）
サリー･シルバーストーン
カルテックで―
嘱託[しょくたく]:commission/charge (person with)|part-time (employee), ミッション:mission, スペシャリスト:specialist, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
嘱託のミッションスペシャリストを
していた
ああ 俺は 星野八郎太
Hi, I'm Hoshino Hachirota.
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
デブリ屋だ
（サリー）星野？
Debris Hauler.
"Hoshino"?
（レオーノフ）いよ～ほう
Wow, I guess we've got ourselves a thoroughbred on the team!
すげえ:incredible/unbelievable, サラブレッド:thoroughbred, 一緒になる[いっしょになる]:to come together/to join
すげえサラブレッドと
一緒になったもんだ
I'm Leonov Norstein. I'm an engineer on a supply transport.
（レオーノフ）
俺は レオーノフ･ノルシュテイン
ライフライン:(essential) utilities, 輸送[ゆそう]:transport/transportation, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 機関士[きかんし]:engineer
ライフライン輸送船の機関士だ
Nice to meet you.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（ハチマキ）よろしく
Hey, isn't there an engineer by the name of Hoshino?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 機関士[きかんし]:engineer
ねえ 確か星野って 機関士に
Chief engineer! The Von Braun's chief engineer!
機関長[きかんちょう]:chief engineer, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
機関長 フォン･ブラウン号のな
They say that Dr. Locksmith recruited him in person.
博士[はかせ, はくし]:doctorate/PhD|expert, 自ら[おのずから]:naturally/as a matter of course, 自ら[みずから]:oneself|for one's self/personally, 誘う[さそう, いざなう]:to invite/to ask|to tempt, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
ロックスミス博士 自ら
誘ったって話だけど？
（サリー）へえ
Yeah. He's my old man.
親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
（ハチマキ）ああ 俺の親父(おやじ)だ
おいおい:Hey!/Wait a minute!|boohoo, おいおい:gradually/by degrees/little by little, サラブレッド:thoroughbred
（レオーノフ）
おいおい 本当にサラブレッドか
Oh, wow, so you really are a thoroughbred?
He's got nothing to do with me! I'm me!
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
関係ねえ 俺は俺だ！
This is test site #24. Applicants 2300 through
2400 are present and accounted for.
Where is Dr. Locksmith?
博士[はかせ, はくし]:doctorate/PhD|expert
（ドルフ）ロックスミス博士は？
He's in the lab, making last-minute tweaks to the system software.
職員[しょくいん]:staff member/personnel, 研究室[けんきゅうしつ]:laboratory|seminar room|professor's office, システムソフト:system, システムソフト:soft, 再調整[さいちょうせい]:readjustment/realignment
（職員１）
研究室でシステムソフトの再調整を
He said he might be in there for a while.
しばらく:little while/short while|a while
しばらくは出てこないかと
Block 32, practical skills examination is complete.
Hard to believe that the guy who came up with a test like this isn't gonna oversee it himself...
酷[こく]:severe/harsh/stringent, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
（係員）
これだけ酷な試験を考えた―
張本人[ちょうほんにん]:ringleader/originator/perpetrator, 立ち会う[たちあう]:to be present/to be witness to
張本人が立ち会わないとはね
Shall we call off the test, then?
職員[しょくいん]:staff member/personnel, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 中止[ちゅうし]:suspension/stoppage/discontinuance
（職員２）
では試験を中止しますか？
Beginning removal of materials used during test.
人道[じんどう, にんどう]:humanity|sidewalk|human realm, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
いや 人道上問題はあるが―
No. There may be some ethical issues with this test,
...but since we're taking on Jupiter, I suppose we can't say that this is too harsh.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 厳しい[きびしい]:severe/strict|intense (e.g. cold), すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time), とは言え[とはいえ]:though/although/be that as it may
木星が相手となれば
厳しすぎるとは言えないだろう
Success rates at exam sites 56 and 62 have fallen slightly.
Keep a close eye on the safety checks.
I don't want any incidents if we can help it.
安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 怠る[おこたる]:to be negligent in doing something/to shirk/to be off one's guard
安全確認を怠るなよ
無事[ぶじ]:safety/peace/quietness, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
できれば無事に終わらせたい
A reorganization of applicant registration has been accepted.
Yes, sir.
職員[しょくいん]:staff member/personnel
（職員１）はい
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
あと１人 遅いわね
One person to go.
He sure is taking his time.
I don't want any weak links.
This is a team effort, you know.
まとい:target shooting (with bow & arrow), 勘弁[かんべん]:pardon/forgiveness/forbearance
足手まといは勘弁な
チーム:team, 戦[いくさ]:war/battle|troops, 戦[せん]:war/battle|match
チーム戦なんだからよ
いよいよ:more and more/all the more|at last
おっ いよいよ お出ましか
Finally here, huh?
いよいよ:more and more/all the more|at last
おっ いよいよ お出ましか
ん？
Hakim!
ハキム
Hoshino, huh? I swear, we can't seem to shake each other.
腐れ縁[くされえん]:(undesirable but) inseparable relationship, まったく:really/truly|indeed
（ハキム）
星野か 腐れ縁だな まったく
What, you two know each other?
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
（レオーノフ）
何だ 知り合いかよ
Fifteen minutes have now elapsed.
経過[けいか]:passage/expiration/progress
（ドルフ）15分 経過です
Teams whose four members are not in their designated module are hereby disqualified.
所定[しょてい]:prescribed/designated/appointed, モジュール:module, そろう:careless/negligent|carelessness, そろう:to become complete/to be all present|to be equal, チーム:team
所定のモジュールに
４名そろっていないチームは―
時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion, 失格[しっかく]:disqualification/elimination/incapacity (legal)
この時点で失格になります
（レオーノフ）あっぶねえ
Geez, that was close!
For the next ten days, you will be testing the cabin's pressure, water, and temperature,
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 日間[ひあい]:number of days/period of days|daily interest rate, 日間[にっかん]:daytime/during the day
（ドルフ）
これから皆さんには10日間―
キャビン:cabin, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 温度[おんど]:temperature, 点検[てんけん]:inspection/examination/checking
キャビン内の空気 水 温度の点検
メンバー:member/participant/attendee, 同士[どうし, どし]:fellow/mutual/companion, 簡易[かんい]:simplicity/convenience/easiness, ヘルス:health, チェック:check/plaid/checkered
メンバー同士の
簡易ヘルスチェック
...along with conducting simple health checks of each member,
および:and/as well as, および:finger/toe/digit, 運動[うんどう]:exercise|appeal|motion, 能力[のうりょく]:ability/faculty, 能力[のうりき]:low-ranking priest who does manual labour at a temple/male temple employee, 測定[そくてい]:measurement
および 運動能力測定
...as well as physical fitness assessments, power system maintenance checks,
電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.), 系[けい]:system|corollary|system (range of strata that correspond to a particular time period)|, メンテナンス:maintenance, チェック:check/plaid/checkered
電源系とメンテナンスチェック
定時[ていじ]:regular time/stated period, キャビン:cabin, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 放射線[ほうしゃせん]:radiation, 磁気[じき]:magnetism, 構成[こうせい]:organization/organisation/configuration, テスト:test, 行う[おこなう]:to perform/to do/to conduct oneself, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
定時のキャビン内放射線
磁気構成テストを行ってもらいます
...as well as periodic in-cabin radiation checks and magnetic calibration tests.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 日常[にちじょう]:ordinary/regular/everyday, 業務[ぎょうむ]:business/affairs/duties
これは
フォン･ブラウン号の日常業務です
These will comprise your daily duties aboard the Von Braun.
Also, there is one more part to this test.
Please note the blue box on the desk.
さらに:furthermore/again/after all, 今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial
さらに今回の試験では もう１つ
デスク:desk, 青い[あおい]:blue|pale|unripe, ボックス:box, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
デスクにある
青いボックスを見てください
期間[きかん]:period/term/interval, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, ボックス:box, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 完成[かんせい]:complete/completion|perfection, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
期間内に そのボックスの中の物を
完成させてもらいます
Assemble the item in the box within the ten-day period.
However, if even one team member should leave the module during the test period,
ただし:but/however/provided that, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, モジュール:module, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|, 場合[ばあい]:case/situation
ただし 試験中に１人でも
モジュールから離れた場合―
...the entire team fails.
チーム:team, 全体[ぜんたい]:whole/entirety/whatever (is the matter), 失格[しっかく]:disqualification/elimination/incapacity (legal)
そのチーム全体が失格となります
Furthermore, no outside communications will be possible during the test period.
期間中[きかんちゅう]:during/for the duration of, 交信[こうしん]:telecommunications/correspondence, 一切[いっさい]:all/everything|absolutely not (with negative), 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
なお 期間中の交信は
一切できません 以上
That is all.
Well, you heard the man.
（レオーノフ）だってよ
とりあえず:first of all/at once|for now, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
（ハチマキ）
とりあえず開けてみるか
Might as well open it up and take a look.
What the heck is this?
何だ？ これ
図面[ずめん]:drawing/diagram/plans
（ハキム）図面がある
（サリー）それは？
Here are some plans.
What is it?
Blueprints for a spaceship.
It's pretty big.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 設計図[せっけいず]:plan/blueprint, 随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
宇宙船の設計図だ 随分と大きいな
（ハチマキ）ああっ
It's the Von Braun.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
フォン･ブラウン号だ
（ハキム）何？
What?
It's a model of the Von Braun.
See this? It's a mirror coil.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 模型[もけい]:model/dummy/maquette
フォン･ブラウン号の模型だよ
ミラー:mirror, コイル:coil
ほら こいつ ミラーコイルだ
Do you think she's gonna work out?
（ラビィ）大丈夫ですかねえ 彼女
（課長）
あっ？ クレアちゃんのこと？
You mean Claire-san?
Sure, why wouldn't she?
だったら 大丈夫じゃない？
She's acted as our supervisor before when she was with Control Section,
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
管制課では
うちの担当だったわけだし―
...and she's lived in space for three years.
年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time)
３年間も
宇宙で暮らしてるんだったら―
I'd rather have her than any of those new...
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
そこらの新人なんかよりずっと…
- That's not what I meant!
そうじゃありませんよ
Claire-san is Hachimaki's old girlfriend, right?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, ハチマキ:headband
クレアさんって確か
ハチマキの前の彼女でしょ
His old girlfriend is all alone with his current one.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, っきり:only/just|since
昔の女と今の女が２人っきり
Something's gonna happen, mark my words!
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
絶対 何か起こりますって
Current one?
今の女って？
I mean Tanabe-kun!
タナベ君ですよ
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
えっ！？
あの２人 つきあってたの？
What?! Those two were going out?!
エーちゃん
E-chan?
あの… クレアさん
Um... Claire-san?
I know that the work in Debris Section is tough and there isn't much hope of advancement,
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, きつい:intense/severe|determined
デブリ課って仕事はきついし―
出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career, 望む[のぞむ]:to desire|to wish for|to see, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
出世も
望めないかもしれないけど―
...but it's not such a bad place!
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
そんな悪いところじゃないですよ
足元[あしもと, そっか]:at one's feet|gait|most recent|, でっかい:huge/big/gargantuan, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe
足元にでっかい地球を見てると―
When you see the big Earth below your feet,
...you can forget all the bad things in life, or things that been bothering you!
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, 悩み[なやみ]:trouble/troubles/worry, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
嫌なこととか悩みとか
忘れられるんですよ
癒やす[いやす]:to heal/to cure
癒やされるっていうか―
It makes you feel better, I guess. Or it makes all your problems seem trivial. It...
ちっぽけ:very small/tiny, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
そういうことが
ちっぽけに思えるっていうか
It...
- Claire Rondo?
ロンド:rondo
その…
（社員）クレア･ロンドさん？
Yes?
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 識別[しきべつ]:discrimination/discernment/identification, 帳[ちょう]:book/register, 帳[とばり]:curtain/hanging/bunting
（クレア）はい
（社員）こちら識別帳になります
This will be your ID tag.
File this form with Control Section.
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 提出[ていしゅつ]:to present/to submit (e.g. a report or a thesis)|presentation, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
管制課のほうに提出してください
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 用事[ようじ]:tasks/things to do/errand
あっ あの… 私 行きます
管制課に行く用事があるんで
Um, I'll take it there. I need to go to Control Section anyway.
Really?
Well, I'll leave you to it, then.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（社員）
ああ そう じゃあ よろしく
Go back to the office without me, Claire-san.
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）それじゃ クレアさんは
先に戻ってください 私は…
I'll take care of...
- I'll go to Control Section.
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（クレア）
管制課には 私が行きます
Huh? But I need to go there anyway.
ついで:next/secondly/subsequently, ついで:opportunity/occasion
（タナベ）えっ でも ついでだから
（クレア）何のついで？
And do what?
Well, um...
えっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えっと あ…
I don't want your sympathy.
同情[どうじょう]:sympathy/compassion/feeling pity for
（クレア）同情はごめんよ
ん…
慢性[まんせい]:chronicity/chronic, 資源[しげん]:resources, 不足[ふそく]:insufficiency/shortage/deficiency, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity
（サリー）
慢性資源不足の人類にとって―
With humanity's chronic shortage of resources,
Jupiter represents our future.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
木星は未来そのものでしょ？
If I'm going to live for a cause,
I'd rather live for the future.
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
何かのために生きるなら
私は未来のために生きたい
カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure
カッコよく言えば そんなところね
It sounds a little dramatic, but I guess that's why.
（ハチマキ）はあ
Hoshino, what made you decide to try to get onto the Von Braun?
（ハキム）星野 どうして 君は―
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
フォン･ブラウンに
乗ろうと思ったんだ？
やっぱり:too/also|still, 親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss, 背中[せなか]:back (of body)
やっぱり あれか？
親父の背中を見てとか
It's the father-son thing, right?
You wanna watch your daddy at work.
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
（ハチマキ）そんなんじゃねえって
ただ乗りたくなったんだよ
That's not it at all.
It's just 'cause I wanna be on her crew.
Why's that?
何？ それ
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
（ハチマキ）
なんか早そうでさ 強そうでさ
'Cause it looks fast. And powerful. And like it could fly to the ends of the universe.
うーんと:hmm/well, 遠く[とおく]:far away/distant/at a distance, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
うーんと遠くまで行けそうで
（レオーノフ）
分かる 分かるなあ 俺もそうだ
I know! I know what you mean!
It's the same for me!
I wanna go as far away as I can.
I wanna leave this dump Earth far behind.
遠く[とおく]:far away/distant/at a distance
俺は遠くへ行きたいんだ
くそったれ:shithead/bastard, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 遠く[とおく]:far away/distant/at a distance
このくそったれな地球を離れて
ずっと遠くによ
Good grief, we've got a couple of bad boys on board.
とんだ:unthinkable/unimaginable|terrible, いたずら:mischief/prank|pastime, いたずら:useless/vain/aimless, 坊主[ぼうず]:Buddhist priest|close-cropped hair|boy|
（サリー）やれやれ
とんだ いたずら坊主たちね
シャワー:shower
シャワー いい？
（レオーノフ）ああ
Done with the shower?
Yeah.
Hakim, how about you?
What's your story?
（ハチマキ）
ハキム あんたはどうして？
You even quit the OSA to take this test.
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954), 辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit
わざわざ軌道保安庁を辞めてまで
If I get selected, I'll tell you.
受かる[うかる]:to pass (examination), 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
受かったら 教えるよ
永遠[えいえん]:eternity/perpetuity/immortality
じゃあ 永遠に分からねえかもな
Then I guess we might never know.
If I don't make the cut, neither will you.
落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
私が落ちたら 君も落ちるんだぞ
あっ…
答え[こたえ, いらえ]:answer/reply/response, 楽しみにする[たのしみにする]:to look forward to something
答えを楽しみにしておこうっと
I look forward to hearing your answer, then.
♪～
I was surprised to hear that they'd put you in the hospital.
驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 入院[にゅういん]:hospitalization/hospitalisation, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（タナベ）驚きました
まさか入院してたなんて
Paging Mr. Fritz Ramsey in room 305.
Please come to the central pharmacy.
I'm only in here for testing.
I've got plenty of time left, Angel.
検査[けんさ]:inspection (e.g. customs, factory)/examination/scan (e.g. MRI, PET, etc.), 入院[にゅういん]:hospitalization/hospitalisation
（ギガルト）ただの検査入院さ
まだまだ:still some way to go before the goal/still more to come/much more, エンジェル:angel
まだまだ大丈夫だ エンジェル
（タナベ）よかった
I'm glad to hear that.
ハチマキ:headband
（ギガルト）ハチマキのことか？
You're calling about Hachimaki?
えっ あ… はい
Um... Yes, sir.
慎重[しんちょう]:careful/cautious/prudent
（サリー）慎重にな
Careful, now...
（レオーノフ）分かってる
I know. I'll be gentle, just like
I was caressing a girl...
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 触れる[ふれる]:to touch|to experience|to touch on a subject||, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
女の子に触れるように優しくだろ？
やった
Got it!
ミッション:mission, コンプリート:complete
（サリー）
ミッション コンプリート
Mission complete!
So, this is the Von Braun, huh?
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown
（ハチマキ）
これがフォン･ブラウンか
There aren't any pieces left over, are there?
部品[ぶひん]:parts/accessories/components, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
（サリー）部品 残ってない？
Don't worry, I checked.
確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（ハキム）大丈夫 確認した
Still, what are they hoping to learn by putting us through a isolated environment test now?
（レオーノフ）しっかし―
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 閉鎖[へいさ]:closing/closure/shutdown, 環境[かんきょう]:environment/circumstance, テスト:test, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
今更 俺たちに
閉鎖環境テストを受けさせて―
楽勝[らくしょう]:easy victory, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
どうしようっての？ 楽勝すぎだろ
This has been a total cakewalk, right?
まだ５時間もある
And we've still got a whole five hours.
Maybe we're just a good team.
At this rate, we...
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, チーム:team
私たち 結構いいチームかもね
このまま…
（レオーノフ）おっ
（ハチマキ）何だ？
What the...?
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, システム:system, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（ハキム）落ち着け
まず システムを確認するんだ
Keep calm. The first order of business is checking the systems.
Okay, I'll take the power box.
電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.), ボックス:box
じゃあ 俺は 電源ボックスを
I'll check for radiation.
放射線[ほうしゃせん]:radiation
私は放射線のほうを
磁気[じき]:magnetism, チェック:check/plaid/checkered
磁気チェックをしよう
I'll do a magnetic check.
やはり:too/also|still
やはりな
Just as I expected. I didn't think it would end this easily.
終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
このままで終わるはずがないとは
思ったが
（タナベ）そうですか
Oh, I see. So, he hasn't gotten in touch with you either, Gigalt-san.
連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
ギガルトさんのところにも
連絡ないんですね
No. Sorry I couldn't help you, Angel.
エンジェル:angel
（ギガルト）
ああ すまんな エンジェル
（タナベ）あっ いえ
That's okay. Thank you for your help.
Take care of yourself.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
ありがとうございました お大事に
ハチマキ:headband, 港[みなと]:harbour/harbor/port, 港[こう]:harbour, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
（ギガルト）ハチマキのやつ
港あってこその船だろうが
That idiot Hachimaki...
This is an announcement from the Medical Section.
He should know that every ship needs a harbor.
The endoscopy center will be undergoing maintenance tomorrow.
Was that Tanabe-san just now?
（ノノ）今のタナベさん？
（ギガルト）うん？
Patients who were scheduled for their regular checkup at that time,
That was Tanabe-san, the debris hauler, wasn't it?
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
（ノノ）デブリ屋さんの
タナベさんでしょう？
ハチマキ:headband, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
ハチマキの友達の
Hachimaki's friend?
...please consult with your primary physician by the end of the day.
We couldn't pinpoint the cause of the accident from inside the module,
モジュール:module
（レオーノフ）
モジュールの中からじゃ―
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, 特定[とくてい]:specific/particular|specifying
事故原因は
特定できなかったが―
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably, 電気[でんき]:electricity|(electric) light, 系統[けいとう]:system|lineage|group (e.g. of colors) (colours)||, 故障[こしょう]:breakdown|damage|objection
恐らく電気系統の故障だ
...but it looks like an electrical system malfunction.
残り[のこり]:remnant/residue/remaining, 電力[でんりょく]:electric power
（ハキム）残りの電力は？
How much power do we have left?
We've got 26 kilowatts stored in the batteries.
蓄電[ちくでん]:storage of electricity, キロワット:kilowatt
（レオーノフ）
蓄電は 26キロワット
If we tweak the control system, we can squeeze out about 3 kilowatts an hour.
制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, 系統[けいとう]:system|lineage|group (e.g. of colors) (colours)||, 調整[ちょうせい]:adjustment/regulation/coordination, ギリギリ:just barely/only just/at the very limit, ギリギリ:grinding (sound)/grating/gnashing, 毎時[まいじ]:every hour/hourly, キロワット:kilowatt, 捻出[ねんしゅつ]:contriving (to raise funds, to find time, etc.)|working out (a solution)
制御系統を調整すれば ギリギリ
毎時３キロワットを捻出できる
But the real problem is our air supply.
問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
だが 問題なのは空気のほうだ
The ventilation filters aren't working?
換気[かんき]:ventilation, フィルター:filter (esp. camera), 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
換気フィルターが動かないのか
If we don't use power for anything else, there's just enough to run the ventilation filters.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 節約[せつやく]:economising/saving, 換気[かんき]:ventilation, 回す[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||
他を節約すれば 換気フェルターを
回すだけはなんとかなる
Then what's the problem?
だったら…
We flat-out don't have enough oxygen.
純粋[じゅんすい]:pure/true/genuine, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
純粋に酸素が足りないんだ
（サリー）ええっ！？
We might have vented it during the accident.
故障[こしょう]:breakdown|damage|objection, 排出[はいしゅつ]:evacuation/emission (e.g. of CO2, etc.)/ejection
（レオーノフ）
故障時に排出されちまったのかもな
（ハキム）ハァ…
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O)
（サリー）残った酸素は？
How much O   do we have left?
約[やく]:approximately|promise|shortening|, グラム:gram/gramme
（レオーノフ）約627グラム
About 627 grams.
酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 消費量[しょうひりょう]:amount of consumption, 当たり[あたり]:hit|success|guess||, グラム:gram/gramme
人の酸素消費量は １時間当たり
34,8グラムだから―
A human's O   consumption is about 34.8 grams per hour,
...so we'd need 696 grams to last the four of us until the end of the test.
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination, グラム:gram/gramme, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
試験終了まで ４人で
696グラム 必要ってことだ
足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
（サリー）足りないじゃない
We don't have enough!
飲料水[いんりょうすい]:drinking water, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
（ハチマキ）
飲料水から酸素を作るのは？
What about making O   from our drinking water?
We don't have anywhere near enough power to even consider electrolysis.
電気分解[でんきぶんかい]:electrolysis, 電力[でんりょく]:electric power, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
（レオーノフ）電気分解しようにも
電力が足りない
What about the oxidizer in our propellant?
推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant, 酸化剤[さんかざい]:oxidizing agent/oxidant/oxidizer
（ハキム）推進剤の酸化剤は？
安定化[あんていか]:stabilization/stabilisation
（レオーノフ）
安定化されてるからな
The problem is that it's stabilized.
たとえ:example|simile/metaphor, たとえ:even if/no matter (what)/if, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 抽出[ちゅうしゅつ]:extraction/abstraction|selection (from a group), 毒性[どくせい]:toxicity/virulence|toxic
たとえ酸素を抽出できても
毒性の強いガスも出る
Even if we could extract the oxygen, it'd also produce a highly toxic gas.
緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency, 与[むた, みた]:together with ..., 圧服[あっぷく]:overpower/subdue/keep down, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
緊急与圧服はないのか？
宇宙船なら…
Aren't there any emergency pressure suits?
A spaceship ought to...
ない
No.
How can you be so sure about that?
言い切る[いいきる]:to declare/to assert|to finish saying
どうしてそう言い切れる
I checked before I came in here.
チェック:check/plaid/checkered, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification
ここに入るまでに
チェックしてきた
There are no pressure suits or air tanks of any kind.
与[むた, みた]:together with ..., 圧服[あっぷく]:overpower/subdue/keep down, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, ボンベ:compressed gas cylinder, 類い[たぐい]:kind/sort|equal
与圧服どころか
ボンベの類いもない
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
それであんなに遅かったのか
So that's why you were so late, huh?
タイムトライアル:time trial
タイムトライアルってわけじゃない
It wasn't a race. I put the time I was given to the most effective use I could.
与える[あたえる]:to give (esp. to someone of lower status)|to provide|to assign||, ギリギリ:just barely/only just/at the very limit, ギリギリ:grinding (sound)/grating/gnashing, 有効[ゆうこう]:valid/effective|yuko (judo), もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
与えられた時間は ギリギリまで
有効に使わせてもらった
（ハチマキ）ああっ…
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, とどめを刺す[とどめをさす]:to finish off|to put an end to|to be the best for A
ありがとう ハキム
とどめを刺してくれて
Thanks so much, Hakim.
You just dashed our last hopes.
空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 棄権[きけん]:abstention (from voting)/renunciation (of a right)/withdrawal (from a contest), トラブル:trouble, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial
空気があるうちに棄権しよう
トラブルなんだから 試験は…
Let's call it quits while we still have air.
It was an accident, so the test is...
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), トラブル:trouble, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
駄目だ 木星でもトラブルは起こる
No way. There'll be mishaps at Jupiter, too.
I know that's what Locksmith would say.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
ロックスミスなら きっとそう言う
（サリー）そんな…
Are you kidding?
He's right.
（ハキム）本当だ
博士[はかせ, はくし]:doctorate/PhD|expert, ニューギニア:New Guinea, 試験場[しけんじょう]:examination hall/examination room|laboratory
ロックスミス博士は
ニューギニア試験場で―
Dr. Locksmith failed all the applicants who were involved...
トラブル:trouble, 巻き込む[まきこむ]:to roll up/to enfold|to involve, 落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||
トラブルに巻き込まれた人間を
落としている
...in a mishap at the New Guinea test center.
トラブル:trouble, 自体[じたい]:itself|one's own body|originally, 仕組む[しくむ]:to devise/to arrange/to plan, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
それに このトラブル自体が
仕組まれている可能性もある
Besides, there's a good chance that this malfunction scenario was planned.
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed, どうり:reason/logic/sense, 簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
なるほどな
どうりで簡単すぎると思ったんだ
Okay, I get it. I thought this was a little too easy.
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial
こっちが本当の試験だっていうの？
You're saying that this is the real test?
I know there's a risk of accidents in these isolated environment tests,
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is, 閉鎖[へいさ]:closing/closure/shutdown, 実験[じっけん]:experiment, アクシデント:accident, 付き物[つきもの]:essential part/indispensable part|front and back matter (of a book, magazine, etc.)
そりゃ 閉鎖実験に
アクシデントは付き物だけど―
...but a life or death situation like this is...
生き死に[いきしに]:life and-or death, 関わる[かかわる]:to be affected|to be concerned with|to stick to (opinions)
こんな生き死にに関わるものを…
試す[ためす]:to attempt/to test/to try out
それを試そうってことだろう？
ロックスミスは
That's what Locksmith wants to test us for.
He's putting our lives at risk to see how we'll handle the real thing.
本番[ほんばん]:performance|game|actual sexual intercourse (i.e. not simulated), 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, 命を懸ける[いのちをかける]:to put one's life on the line/to risk one's life/to put everything one has into it, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
本番でどう動くか
俺たちに命を懸けさせて
手伝い[てつだい]:helper/assistant|help, 整備[せいび]:maintenance/servicing|putting in place, リスト:list
（フィー）クレア
月の手伝いで使う整備リストを―
Claire? Take that maintenance list we'll be using when we help out on the moon...
提出[ていしゅつ]:to present/to submit (e.g. a report or a thesis)|presentation
ベイオフィスに提出しといて
...and submit it at the Bay Office, okay?
The check sheet is on Tanabe's desk.
チェックシート:check/plaid/checkered, チェックシート:seat, 机[つくえ, つき]:desk
チェックシートは
タナベの机にあるから
（クレア）はい
Sure.
フィー:phi, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 休暇[きゅうか]:holiday/day off/furlough, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
フィーさん 愛ちゃん ずっと
休暇 取ってないんだけど大丈夫？
Fee-san, Ai-chan hasn't taken any days off for a long time now. Is she gonna be okay?
She says she wants to go out, so I won't ask her to.
本人[ほんにん]:the person himself
本人が出たいって聞かないんだ
まっ ハチもいないことだし―
Anyway, I'm glad to have her out there in the field now that Hachi's not around.
現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor, ありがたい:grateful/thankful/welcome
現場としては
ありがたいんだけどね
（課長）でもさあ
But still...
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
頑張りたいときってのは
あるもんさ
Sometimes you want to tough things out.
Relax, I'll keep an eye on her.
フォロー:follow
大丈夫 フォローはするよ
Really? With that Supreme Council meeting coming up on the moon,
（課長）そう？
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
月での最高評議会もあるし
何かと大変だと思うけど頼むね
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
月での最高評議会もあるし
何かと大変だと思うけど頼むね
あっ…
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
月での最高評議会もあるし
何かと大変だと思うけど頼むね
...I think that things are going to be hectic, so take care of her, okay?
See it?
（フィー）あるだろ？
（クレア）あっ…
It's the one with the blue cover.
青い[あおい]:blue|pale|unripe, 表紙[ひょうし]:front cover/binding|appearing on the cover of a magazine
（フィー）青い表紙のやつ
（クレア）はい
Right.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 休暇[きゅうか]:holiday/day off/furlough, 代わりになる[かわりになる]:to substitute for/to stand in for/to fill in for
（社員１）
いい休暇代わりになったな
That was a pretty good makeshift vacation, huh?
（チェンシン）はあ
Yes.
（タナベ）チェンシンさん
（チェンシン）あっ
Cheng-Shin-san!
Welcome back, Cheng-Shin-san.
おかえりなさい:welcome home
（タナベ）
おかえりなさい チェンシンさん
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently, 社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（チェンシン）ただいま
（社員１）なんだ 彼女か？
It's good to be back.
Who's this, your girlfriend?
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 色男[いろおとこ]:lover/lady-killer/sexy guy
さすがだなあ 色男
Way to go, loverboy!
（チェンシン）
そんなんじゃありません！
It's not like that!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.)
（社員１）ああっ… じゃあ
俺たち 先に行くからな
I guess we'll go on ahead, then.
- See you on tomorrow's flight.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, あした:morning, あした:tomorrow|near future, フライト:flight
（社員２）あした フライトで
Sure.
（チェンシン）はい
どうしたんだ？ あいつ
What's the matter with him?
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
（社員２）試験 終わってから
なんかおかしいんですよ
He's been acting kinda funny ever since the test ended.
I'm glad to see you. I didn't expect you to welcome me back.
うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
（チェンシン）うれしいよ
出迎える[でむかえる]:to meet/to greet, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
君が出迎えてくれるなんて
思わなかったから
Um... Is it true that Senpai passed the first round of testing?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 受かる[うかる]:to pass (examination), たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, ほんと:truth/reality|proper
あの… 先輩は １次試験に
受かったって ほんとですか？
Where's the second round being held?
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 会場[かいじょう]:assembly hall/meeting place/venue
２次試験の会場って
どこなんですか？
Do you think they'd let me see him?
Or maybe I could leave a phone message...
面会[めんかい]:meeting (face-to-face)/interview, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), 取り次ぎ[とりつぎ]:agency|reception (of guests)|conveyance (of messages)
面会ってできるんでしょうか？
電話の取り次ぎは？
残酷[ざんこく]:cruelty/harshness
残酷だね
That's really cruel.
えっ？
I failed the first round of tests, and you're asking me about the second round?
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
（チェンシン）
１次試験で落ちた僕に―
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
２次のことを聞くなんて
あっ…
ハチマキ:headband, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 恋人[こいびと]:lover/sweetheart, 要る[いる]:to need/to want
（チェンシン）ハチマキは
友達も恋人も要らないってさ
Hachimaki said that he doesn't need friends or girlfriends.
えっ？
生きていく[いきていく, いきてゆく]:to subsist/to keep on living
あいつは１人で生きていくよ
He'll live his life alone.
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 友人[ゆうじん]:friend, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
会社も友人も
地球すら必要ないんだ
He doesn't need a company, or friends, or even the Earth.
でも 僕は…
（タナベ）あ…
But not me!
There are things that I want!
Dreams and girls that I want!
欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
僕だって欲しいものはあるんだ！
夢[ゆめ]:dream
夢だって女だって
（タナベ）チェンシンさん？
Cheng-Shin-san?
欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to, 奪う[うばう]:to snatch away/to dispossess/to steal, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
欲しいと思ってるさ
奪ってでも手に入れたいって！
I want them! And I'll get them, even if I have to steal them!
（タナベ）あ…
（チェンシン）うっ
あっ… かんだ
You bit me?
If you ever do that again,
I'll bite your lip off.
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, かみちぎる:to bite off
今度やったら かみちぎります
（チェンシン）はっ
うっ…
（チェンシン）
うっ タナベさん あっ くっ…
Tanabe-san!
なっ…
らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
らしくないかい？
I'm not acting like myself?
Not really.
（クレア）そうね
（チェンシン）僕にだってさ―
There are things that I want.
Things that I'm willing to chase after.
追いすがる[おいすがる]:to be hot on a person's heels, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
追いすがってでも
手に入れたいものくらい あるんだ
（タナベ）違う
He's wrong. Senpai's not like that.
He'd never want to live alone!
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
１人でいいなんて
先輩はそんな人じゃない！
あっ
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（レオーノフ）駄目だ！
It's useless! We can't do anything from in here!
やっぱり:too/also|still
やっぱり中からじゃ
どうにもならねえよ！
大声[おおごえ, たいせい]:loud voice, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
（サリー）
大声 出さないで 酸素がなくなる
Stop shouting!
You're using up our oxygen.
（レオーノフ）ふん！
Hey, where are you going?
（ハチマキ）おい どこに行く
I'm going outside and calling for help.
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 助け[たすけ]:assistance/help/aid, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
外に出て 助けを呼んでくるんだよ
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 失格[しっかく]:disqualification/elimination/incapacity (legal)
やめろ！ そんなことしたら
全員失格になる
Forget it! If you do that, we'll all be disqualified!
It's better than dying!
死ぬよりマシだ
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（ハチマキ）駄目だ
Don't! There's an airlock between us and them.
There's a chance that it vented.
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, エアロック:air lock, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 抜く[ぬく]:to extract|to do something to the end|to surpass||, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
間にエアロックがあるんだぞ
酸素が抜かれている可能性だって
知るか
Like I care!
わがまま:selfishness/egoism|disobedience
わがまま言ってんじゃねえよ
Stop thinking about only yourself!
I'm getting onto the Von Braun, even if it costs me my life!
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
死んでも
フォン･ブラウン号に乗るんだ
死ぬ[しぬ]:to die|to lose spirit|to cease
だったら１人で死ねよな
Die by yourself, then. We'd have enough air with only three people in here.
酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
３人だけなら酸素も足りるだろうさ
ああっ…
（ハキム）ほう ３人か
Hm... Three people.
That's an interesting suggestion, Leonov.
興味[きょうみ]:interest (in something)/curiosity (about something)/zest (for), 深い[ふかい]:deep|profound|dense||, 提案[ていあん]:proposal/proposition/suggestion
興味深い提案だな レオーノフ
（サリー）
えっ？ ちょ… ちょっと
H-Hey, wait a minute...
残り[のこり]:remnant/residue/remaining, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), グラム:gram/gramme
（ハチマキ）
残りの酸素は 490グラム
We've got 490 grams of O2 left.
That's enough to keep three people alive.
十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 分量[ぶんりょう]:amount/quantity
３人だけなら
十分に生きられる分量だな
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
（レオーノフ）
どういう意味だよ お前ら
What the hell are you two implying?
バカなことを言わないで
Don't be stupid! This is also supposed to be a test of our teamwork.
チームワーク:teamwork, 試す[ためす]:to attempt/to test/to try out, テスト:test, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
これは チームワークを
試すテストでもあるのよ
Teamwork's important, all right.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, チームワーク:teamwork, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
（ハチマキ）
もちろん チームワークは大事だ
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
うん そのとおりだな しかし…
It certainly is. However...
普段[ふだん]:usual/habitual/ordinary, チームワーク:teamwork
（レオーノフ）
へっ 普段のチームワークと―
Your point's that regular teamwork is different from teamwork in an emergency, right?
緊急時[きんきゅうじ]:emergency
緊急時のそれは
違うって言いたいんだろう？
Yeah. When you're short on oxygen, what's important isn't to keep everyone alive,
酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
（ハチマキ）
ああ 酸素が足りない以上―
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped
大事なのは
全員が助かることじゃなくて―
...but to keep everyone from dying!
全滅[ぜんめつ]:annihilation/total destruction/complete destruction
全滅しないことだ
Are you seriously suggesting this?
本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth
本気で言ってんのか？
I have to get on board the Von Braun!
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
俺は フォン･ブラウンに
乗らなきゃいけないんだ！
生き残る[いきのこる]:to survive, 限る[かぎる]:to restrict/to limit|to be restricted to
しかし 生き残るほうの３人に
お前が入るとは限らないな
Maybe, but you're not necessarily gonna be one of the three survivors.
みせる:to show/to display
フンッ 私だって
３人のほうに入ってみせる
I'm gonna make damn sure that I'm one of those three!
（サリー）あっ
サリー:sari, 非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, ボタン:button, ボタン:tree peony (Paeonia suffruticosa)/moutan, 手を出す[てをだす]:to turn one's hand to|to get involved in|to start a fight
サリー 非常ボタンに手を出すなよ
Sally, keep your hand away from that emergency button.
意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising, 甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate
（サリー）
フンッ 意外と甘いのね 星野
You're softer than I expected, Hoshino.
The truth is, you're not sure, are you?
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
実は迷っているんじゃない？
（ハチマキ）あっ
You're not sure you can murder someone.
Well, don't push yourself!
人殺し[ひとごろし]:murder/murderer, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
（サリー）人殺しなんて
無理しないほうがいいわよ
ああっ
（ハキム）ううっ
（サリー）うっ うう…
（ハキム）んんん…
サリー:sari, 傷つける[きずつける]:to wound|to hurt someone's feelings (pride, etc.)|to damage, 非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, ボタン:button, ボタン:tree peony (Paeonia suffruticosa)/moutan
サリー 仲間を傷つけて
非常ボタンというのは―
Sally, I can't let you wound one of us and push the emergency button.
同意[どうい]:agreement/consent|same meaning
同意できないな
じゃあ どうするつもり？
What do you suggest we do, then?
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 生き残る[いきのこる]:to survive, 腹[はら]:abdomen|womb|one's mind||
てめえも ３人で
生き残ろうって腹だろ？
I thought you were on board with the whole "three survivors" plan.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
（ハキム）
私は 絶対にフォン･ブラウン号に
乗ると決めている
I'm determined to get onto
the Von Braun, no matter the cost.
Even if that means committing a crime to do it.
たとえ:example|simile/metaphor, たとえ:even if/no matter (what)/if, 犯罪[はんざい]:crime/offence/offense, 犯す[おかす]:to commit (e.g. crime)|to break (e.g. rule)|to rape, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
たとえ そのために
犯罪を犯すことになっても
殺人[さつじん]:murder
（レオーノフ）それが殺人でもか！
Even if it means murder?!
そうだ
That's right.
だが まだ時間はある
（サリー）ええっ
But we still have time before it comes to that.
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination
（ハキム）試験終了まで４時間
The test ends in four hours.
If only three of us will be alive, we can last three and a half hours.
生き残る[いきのこる]:to survive, 残り[のこり]:remnant/residue/remaining, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 耐える[たえる]:to bear|to support|to be fit for
３人が生き残るだけなら
残り３時間半までは耐えられる
We'll try to think of another way in the next thirty minutes.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
あと30分
他に方法がないか考えるんだ
Hakim...
（ハチマキ）ハキム
Don't give up. Not until the bitter end.
諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to), 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
（ハキム）諦めるな 最後まで
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（レオーノフ）
考えて 駄目だったら？
What if we think it over and still can't think of a way?
If that happens, I'll kill one of you.
（ハキム）
そのときは 私が誰かを―
殺す
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 分解[ぶんかい]:disassembly|factorization|decomposition|
（受験者１）
空気分解はやったのか？
Did you try electrolysis?
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee, とっく:a long time ago|quickly/swiftly, とっく:special ward|special economic zone (China)
（受験者２）とっくにやってる
I've been trying!
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee, 押す[おす]:to push|to apply pressure from above|to stamp (i.e. a passport)||, ボタン:button, ボタン:tree peony (Paeonia suffruticosa)/moutan
（受験者３）押すぞ ボタン
（受験者４）まだだ！
Let's push the button!
Not yet!
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 電圧[でんあつ]:voltage
（受験者５）あと どれくらい？
（受験者６）電圧がさ…
How much longer?
There's not enough current!
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee, 巻き添え[まきぞえ]:getting mixed up in/getting embroiled in/involvement
（受験者７）巻き添えはゴメンだ！
You're not gonna take me out with you!
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee
（受験者８）何やってんのよ
You dumb bastard!
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee
（受験者１）バカ野郎！
If you hadn't pushed the button, we...
ボタン:button, ボタン:tree peony (Paeonia suffruticosa)/moutan, 押す[おす]:to push|to apply pressure from above|to stamp (i.e. a passport)||
お前がボタンを押さなきゃ
俺たちは…
受験者[じゅけんしゃ]:examinee, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 懸ける[かける]:to hang (e.g. picture)|to sit|to take (time, money)||, 電気分解[でんきぶんかい]:electrolysis
（受験者２）命まで懸けてられるか
（受験者３）電気分解？
- You think I'm gonna risk my life over this?!
Electrolysis? We didn't have the power to spare!
余裕[よゆう]:surplus/margin|composure, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
そんな余裕なんてなかっただろう
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, モジュール:module, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 救急[きゅうきゅう]:first-aid/emergency (aid), 要請[ようせい]:appeal/call for something|axiom
（係員）第５モジュール
状況確認 救急要請なし
Module 5, confirming situation.
- Module 12, confirming situation.
No request for assistance. Repeating...
- One to be carried out. Vitals check...
バイタル:vital, チェック:check/plaid/checkered, 開始[かいし]:start/commencement/beginning, 繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again
バイタルチェック開始 繰り返す…
All right, it's time. The test is over.
（ドルフ）時間だな
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination, 追加[ついか]:addition/supplement/append (e.g. to a file), 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), および:and/as well as, および:finger/toe/digit, 電力[でんりょく]:electric power, 供給[きょうきゅう]:supply/provision
試験終了
追加酸素 および電力を供給
Supply the modules with
additional oxygen and power.
救護班[きゅうごはん]:relief squad/rescue party, エアロック:air lock, 出口[でぐち]:exit/gateway/way out, 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity
救護班は エアロック出口で待機
Rescue teams, stand by outside the airlocks.
After checking the pressure inside the airlocks, verify the situation inside the capsules.
エアロック:air lock, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 気圧[きあつ]:atmospheric pressure, チェック:check/plaid/checkered, 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, モジュール:module, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
エアロック内の気圧をチェック後
モジュール内の状況を確認
If an applicant appears to be in poor physical condition,
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 本人[ほんにん]:the person himself, 申し出[もうしで, もうしいで]:proposal/request/claim
受験生本人からの
申し出がなくとも―
...take them to the medical center as needed even if they do not ask for treatment.
体調不良[たいちょうふりょう]:poor physical health/bad shape, 疑い[うたがい]:doubt/question/uncertainty, 随時[ずいじ]:as needed/as occasion demands|at any time, 医療[いりょう]:medical care/medical treatment, センター[センター, センタ]:centre/center
体調不良の疑いがある者は
随時 医療センターへ
搬送[はんそう]:transportation/conveyance|hospitalization, ブロック:to block (e.g. the way), 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity, 班[はん]:group/party|squad, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
搬送は別ブロックにて
待機中の１班が担当する
The handle's not turning!
Transport will be carried out by the transport teams that are standing by in another block.
搬送[はんそう]:transportation/conveyance|hospitalization, ブロック:to block (e.g. the way), 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity, 班[はん]:group/party|squad, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
搬送は別ブロックにて
待機中の１班が担当する
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, ハンドル:handle, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
（救護係１）ハンドルが回らない
搬送[はんそう]:transportation/conveyance|hospitalization, ブロック:to block (e.g. the way), 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity, 班[はん]:group/party|squad, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
搬送は別ブロックにて
待機中の１班が担当する
搬送[はんそう]:transportation/conveyance|hospitalization, ブロック:to block (e.g. the way), 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity, 班[はん]:group/party|squad, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
搬送は別ブロックにて
待機中の１班が担当する
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, レスキュー:rescue, ハッチ:hatch, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
（救護係１）
レスキューハッチを開けよう
Let's pop the rescue hatch.
搬送[はんそう]:transportation/conveyance|hospitalization, ブロック:to block (e.g. the way), 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity, 班[はん]:group/party|squad, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
搬送は別ブロックにて
待機中の１班が担当する
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 室温[しつおん]:room temperature
（救護係１）ああっ… 室温が？
Why's it so cold?
うん？
ああっ… 死んでる！
Is she dead?!
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
おい！ なんてことだ おい！
Hey! What the hell happened?! Hey!
I can't believe it, are they all...
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, モニター:(computer) monitor, 班[はん]:group/party|squad
（救護係２）まさか全員…
モニター班は何やってたんだ！？
Were the monitor teams asleep up there?!
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
（救護係１）
いや 大丈夫だ 生きてる
No, she's okay. She's alive.
But her body temp's 28 Celsius!
体温[たいおん]:temperature/body temperature (human, animal), 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol)
しかし 体温が28度に
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol)
（救護係２）28度！？
28 Celsius?!
救助隊[きゅうじょたい]:rescue team or party, 到着[とうちゃく]:arrival
ああ… 救助隊のご到着だ
So, the rescue squad finally graces us with their presence, huh?
- This is module 102! Call the medical staff!
Stat!
I guess this means we beat the secondary test...
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 突破[とっぱ]:breaking through/breakthrough/penetration
これで ２次試験突破だな
Oh, I get it. You lowered your body temperature to slow your metabolism...
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 体温[たいおん]:temperature/body temperature (human, animal), 下げる[さげる]:to hang|to lower|to demote|
（救護係１）
そうか 体温を下げて―
新陳代謝[しんちんたいしゃ]:renewal/replacement/metabolism, 遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|, 酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), 消費量[しょうひりょう]:amount of consumption, 抑える[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|
新陳代謝を遅くして
酸素消費量を抑えたのか
...to minimize your oxygen consumption, right?
"Operation: Hibernation" was a success...
冬眠[とうみん]:hibernation/winter sleep, 作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit
（ハチマキ）冬眠作戦 成功
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 終わり[おわり]:the end
（救護係２）
しっかりしろ 試験は終わりだ
Hang in there. The test is over.
（レオーノフ）んん…
How long have you been like this?
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 何時間[なんじかん]:how many hours?
（救護係２）
何時間 こうしている？
Gimme some D-serum.
The woman can't move.
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 液[えき]:liquid/fluid, 液[しる, つゆ]:juice|soup|(dipping) sauce, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（救護係１）
Ｄ液をくれ 女のほうが動けない
救護[きゅうご]:relief/aid, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge
（救護係２）ああ
Coming.
（ハチマキ）あっ… あ あ…
ハキム
Hakim...
（ハキム）ん…
Were you really willing to kill somebody back then?
あのとき 本当に
誰かを殺すつもりだったのか？
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
もちろんだ
Of course I was.
Space isn't forgiving enough to let people pretend to be friends, and you know it.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, ごっこ:playing at (something)/game of make-believe/something done together, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate
友達ごっこができるほど
宇宙は甘くないだろ？
（ハチマキ）くっ…
（ハキム）ん？
If I was working with you,
I think I could make it to Jupiter.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
あんたとなら 木星に行けそうだ
（ハキム）うん
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Tandem Mirror
ようこそ:welcome!/nice to see you!, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
（ロックスミス）ようこそ
フォン･ブラウン号へ
Welcome aboard the Von Braun.
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, 卒業[そつぎょう]:graduation/completion (e.g. of a course)|outgrowing something
（コリン）
こないだ大学を卒業してね
I graduated from college a while ago.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement
今は 連合の
開発監査部にいるんだ
I work for the INTO Development Inspector's Office now.
はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
いいさ はっきり
見えないくらいのほうが
That's fine. It'll be better if they can't get a good look at me.
（ノノ）あっ…
入港[にゅうこう]:entry into port, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
入港前に デブリの回収？
Pick up debris before we even get to port?
This looks like a section of the tandem mirror engine.
（ユーリ）どうやら―
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document)
タンデムミラーエンジンの
一部のようだな
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
（ハチマキ）俺のことだろ
お前に話してどうすんだよ
It was my decision, wasn't it? What's the point of talking it over with you?
えっ…
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
また愛？
You and your love again... Your love is shallow and meaningless!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 薄っぺらい[うすっぺらい]:very thin/flimsy/cheap
あなたの愛は
薄っぺらいのよ